When you web app
is causing a scandal
Try the "Elements" in
the Sources panel
When you Javascript
is making making a blunder
Use the console and
JavaScript debugger
When a web page is
a cause in bandwidth stress
The network panel
shows you the request
So speed up your page
with just a few rules
It's time to discover
DevTools
If you've been a developer
for a while,
odds are you remember
the battle days
of web development
debugging.
If you get a JavaScript
error in your web page,
well, maybe the browser
gives you a line number,
maybe it doesn't
and maybe that
line number brings
you to where the
error actually happened.
Same thing goes for
stylesheet debugging.
You have a CSS
property and
why isn't it showing up
on the page?!
Well, you go back to your file,
you update it, check the browser.
You're back to the file,
update it, check your browser.
Luckily, these days we have
Chrome Developer Tools.
Developer Tools allows
you to do things like
live edit your HTML and
CSS right there in the page.
It comes with a powerful
JavaScript debugger,
and also a bunch of tools
to optimize your website performance.
It makes programming
for the web...
dare I say...
Easy.
I'm Greg Pollock,
and in this course,
we're gonna be walking
through all the major features
of Chrome Developer Tools.
Now, we're gonna start
with some of the basics
which you already
may be familiar with,
so feel free to skip
ahead to the next couple
chapters
to get into the more
advanced material.
Meanwhile, in Level 1,
we're gonna be jumping
into the Elements panel.
Throughout the videos and the challenges,
we're gonna be working with a scheduling app
which we've been working on --
that you can see here.
We wanna make some
changes to this application.
First thing we'll want to do
is open Developer Tools.
To do that, we look for the icon
on our browser with the 3 lines on it.
Then, find the "Tools" menu item,
then click on "Developer Tools".
If you're not already familiar
with the keyboard shortcut
to call up Developer Tools and to close
Developer Tools from within your browser,
take note of it here, listed
next to the menu item.
It will be much more convenient to open it
using that keyboard shortcut next time.
By default, DevTools will appear at the bottom
part of your Chrome window.
You can close it anytime, either by clicking
that "x" icon in the top left
or simply by using
our keyboard shortcut.
So here in our calendar application,
we wanna make some changes to
the HTML structure of it.
Now, we could go back onto our server
and make the changes there,
and then refresh our
browser,
but maybe we just wanna play around
and live edit the page.
To do that, we wanna make sure
we're in the Elements panel you see here.
In this panel, you can see
a bunch of HTML on the left-side,
and a bunch of CSS on the right.
But what you're really seeing
there on the left side
is a representation of the DOM,
or Document Object Model.
You can think of it as a collection of
the different elements
in your HTML put into
sort of a tree format.
So, if you want, you can press
on those ittle triangle shapes
and it will show you
more or less code
in that document tree.
If you're looking at
your rendered HTML page
and you're
wondering, well,
what element created
that particular element,
what you can do is:
right-click on the element,
(in our case, we're gonna click on the button)
and select "Inspect Element".
This will open the Elements panel,
if we don't already have it opened,
and shows us that particular
element highlighted inside the DOM.
You might also notice that
it's showing us the CSS
for that element on the right side,
but we'll get more
into that on the next level.
Another way you can select an element
is by clicking the magnifying glass
in the bottom-left of the screen
to enter the Element Selection Mode.
Then, when you hover
over the page,
you can see the different
element boundaries
and when you left-click on one,
it will select that element
in the Elements panel.
Now, let's go ahead and
make some live changes.
For example, let's change
the text on our button.
To change that text,
all we have to do is
double-click
on it,
type a new title,
and then we can just hit Enter
when we're done
or click somewhere else on the page.
If we right-click on a particular element,
we're given a bunch
of different options,
including the ability to
add or edit attributes.
Let's go ahead and add an
"id" attribute to this element.
Pretty easy.
Also in this menu,
we can choose
to edit a node
as HTML
where we can change any part of the
element or add additional elements.
Finally, if we click and
drag an element,
we can change its
location on the page.
Finally, if we click and
drag an element,
we can change its
location on the page.
It shouldn't come
as a surprise that
you can select any element
and hit the delete button
to remove
that element
or even right-click and select the
"Delete" menu item.
Well, now it's time for you to practice
using some of these
techniques and the challenges.